But it turns out that the brain's default state is really more like a car idling in drive than a car in park. Some of what we think we choose to do is actually things that we have become programmed to do when the brakes are released. Have you ever joked that your brain was running on autopilot? Guess what? It probably was. OK? And the brain's autopilot is in a structure called the striatum. So the striatum detects emotional and sensory motor conditions and it knows to trigger whatever behavior you have done most often in the past under those same conditions. Do you know why I became a neuroscientist? Because I wanted to learn what made me tick. (Laughter) Thank you, thank you. I've been wanting to use that one in front of an audience for years. (Applause) So in graduate school, I studied genetic factors that orchestrate wiring to the striatum during development. And yes, that is my former license plate. (Laughter) And for the record, I don't recommend any PhD student get a license plate with their thesis topic printed on it, unless they're prepared for their experiments not to work for the next two years. (Laughter) I eventually did figure it out. So, my experiments were exploring how miswiring in the striatum relates to compulsive behaviors. Meaning, behaviors that are coerced by uncomfortable urges you can't consciously resist. So I was really excited when my mice developed this compulsive behavior, where they were rubbing their faces and they couldn't seem to stop, even when they were wounding themselves. OK, excited is the wrong word, I actually felt terrible for them. I thought that they had tics, evidence of striatal miswiring. And they were compulsive, but it turned out, on further testing, that these mice showed an aversion to interacting and getting to know other unfamiliar mice. Which was unusual, it was unexpected. The results implied that the striatum, which, for sure, is involved in compulsive-spectrum disorders, is also involved in human social connection and our ability to -- not human social connection, but our ability to connect. So I delved deeper, into a field called social neuroscience. And that is a newer, interdisciplinary field, and there I found reports that linked the striatum not just to social anomalies in mice, but also in people. As it turns out, the social neurochemistry in the striatum is linked to things you've probably already heard of. Like oxytocin, which is that hormone that makes cuddling feel all warm and fuzzy. But it also implicates signaling at opioid receptors. There are naturally occurring opioids in your brain that are deeply linked to social processes. Experiments with naloxone, which blocks opioid receptors, show us just how essential this opioid-receptor signaling is to social interaction. When people are given naloxone -- it's an ingredient in Narcan, that reverses opioid overdoses to save lives. But when it's given to healthy people, it actually interfered with their ability to feel connected to people they already knew and cared about. So, something about not having opioid-receptor binding makes it difficult for us to feel the rewards of social interaction. Now, for the interest of time, I've necessarily gotten rid of some of the scientific details, but briefly, here's where we're at. The effects of social disconnection through opioid receptors, the effects of addictive drugs and the effects of abnormal neurotransmission on involuntary movements and compulsive behaviors all converge in the striatum. And the striatum and opioid signaling in it has been deeply linked with loneliness. When we don't have enough signaling at opioid receptors, we can feel alone in a room full of people we care about and love, who love us. Social neuroscientists, like Dr. Cacioppo at the University of Chicago, have discovered that loneliness is very dangerous. And it predisposes people to entire spectrums of physical and mental illnesses. Think of it like this: when you're at your hungriest, pretty much any food tastes amazing, right? So similarly, loneliness creates a hunger in the brain which neurochemically hypersensitizes our reward system. And social isolation acts through receptors for these naturally occurring opioids and other social neurotransmitters to leave the striatum in a state where its response to things that signal reward and pleasure is completely, completely over the top. And in this state of hypersensitivity, our brains signal deep dissatisfaction. We become restless, irritable and impulsive. And that's pretty much when I want you to keep the bowl of Halloween chocolate entirely across the room for me, because I will eat it all. I will. And that brings up another thing that makes social disconnection so dangerous. If we don't have the ability to connect socially, we are so ravenous for our social neurochemistry to be rebalanced, we're likely to seek relief from anywhere. And if that anywhere is opioid painkillers or heroin, it is going to be a heat-seeking missile for our social reward system. Is it any wonder people in today's world are becoming addicted so easily? Social isolation -- excuse me -- contributes to relapse. Studies have shown that people who tend to avoid relapse tend to be people who have broad, reciprocal social relationships where they can be of service to each other, where they can be helpful. Being of service lets people connect. So -- if we don't have the ability to authentically connect, our society increasingly lacks this ability to authentically connect and experience things that are transcendent and beyond ourselves. We used to get this transcendence from a feeling of belonging to our families and our communities. But everywhere, communities are changing. And social and economic disintegration is making this harder and harder. I'm not the only person to point out that the areas in the country most economically hard hit, where people feel most desolate about their life's meaning, are also the places where there have been communities most ravaged by opioids. Social isolation acts through the brain's reward system to make this state of affairs literally painful. So perhaps it's this pain, this loneliness, this despondence that's driving so many of us to connect with whatever we can. Like food. Like handheld electronics. And for too many people, to drugs like heroin and fentanyl. I know someone who overdosed, who was revived by Narcan, and she was mostly angry that she wasn't simply allowed to die. Imagine for a second how that feels, that state of hopelessness, OK? But the striatum is also a source of hope. Because the striatum gives us a clue of how to bring people back. So, remember that the striatum is our autopilot, running our behaviors on habit, and it's possible to rewire, to reprogram that autopilot, but it involves neuroplasticity. So, neuroplasticity is the ability of brains to reprogram themselves, and rewire themselves, so we can learn new things. And maybe you've heard the classic adage of plasticity: neurons that fire together, wire together. Right? So we need to practice social connective behaviors instead of compulsive behaviors, when we're lonely, when we are cued to remember our drug. We need neuronally firing repeated experiences in order for the striatum to undergo that necessary neuroplasticity that allows it to take that "go find heroin" autopilot offline. And what the convergence of social neuroscience, addiction and compulsive-spectrum disorders in the striatum suggests is that it's not simply enough to teach the striatum healthier responses to compulsive urges. We need social impulses to replace drug-cued compulsive behaviors, because we need to rebalance, neurochemically, our social reward system. And unless that happens, we're going to be left in a state of craving. No matter what besides our drug we repeatedly practice doing. I believe that the solution to the opioid crisis is to explore how social and psychospiritual interventions can act as neurotechnologies in circuits that process social and drug-induced rewards. One possibility is to create and study scalable tools for people to connect with one another over a mutual interest in recovery through psychospiritual practices. And as such, psychospiritual practice could involve anything from people getting together as megafans of touring jam bands, or parkour jams, featuring shared experiences of vulnerability and personal growth, or more conventional things, like recovery yoga meetups, or meetings centered around more traditional conceptions of spiritual experiences. But whatever it is, it needs to activate all of the neurotransmitter systems in the striatum that are involved in processing social connection. Social media can't go deep enough for this. Social media doesn't so much encourage us to share, as it does to compare. It's the difference between having superficial small talk with someone and authentic, deeply connected conversation with eye contact. And stigma also keeps us separate. There's a lot of evidence that it keeps us sick. And stigma often makes it safer for addicts to connect with other addicts. But recovery groups centered around reestablishing social connections could certainly be inclusive of people who are seeking recovery for a range of mental health problems. My point is, when we connect around what's broken, we connect as human beings. We heal ourselves from the compulsive self-destruction that was our response to the pain of disconnection. When we think of neuropsychiatric illnesses as a spectrum of phenomenon that are part of what make us human, then we remove the otherness of people who struggle with self-destruction. We remove the stigma between doctors and patients and caregivers. We put the question of what it means to be normal versus sick back on the spectrum of the human condition. And it is on that spectrum where we can all connect and seek healing together, for all of our struggles with humanness. Thank you for letting me share. (Applause)
Pero resulta que el estado del cerebro por defecto se parece más a un carro con el motor en espera que a uno estacionado. Algunas de las cosas que creemos que decidimos hacer son en realidad cosas para las que estamos programados cuando se suelta los frenos. ¿Alguna vez han bromeado sobre tener el cerebro en piloto automático? ¿Adivinen qué? Probablemente lo estaba. ¿Bien? Y el piloto automático está en una estructura llamada cuerpo estriado. Este detecta las condiciones emocionales y motores sensoriales y activa el comportamiento más reciente ejecutado bajo esas mismas condiciones. ¿Saben por qué me volví una neurocientífica? Porque quería saber qué producía mis tics. (Risas) Gracias, gracias. Había querido usarla frente a una audiencia por años. (Aplausos) En la universidad, estudié factores genéticos que orquestan el cableado al cuerpo estriado durante el desarrollo. Y sí, esa fue mi antigua placa del carro. (Risas) Y para que conste, no le recomiendo a ningún estudiante de doctorado que usen su tesis como placa de carro, a menos que estén preparados para que sus experimentos no funcionen por 2 años. (Risas) Finalmente lo descubrí. Mis experimentos exploraban cómo fallas de cableado en el cuerpo estriado se relaciona con conductas compulsivas. No podemos resistirnos a aquellas conductas generadas por impulsos incómodos. Me emocioné cuando mis ratones desarrollaron esta conducta compulsiva, en la que se frotaban la cara y parecía que no podían parar, a pesar de hacerse daño. Bien, emocionada no es la palabra adecuada, de hecho me sentía mal por ellos. Pensé que tenían tics, evidencia de error en el cableado del estriado. Y eran compulsivos, Pero luego de más pruebas, resultó que estos ratones mostraban una aversión a interactuar y conocer a otros ratones desconocidos. Esto nos resultó inusual, fue inesperado. Los resultados mostraron que el cuerpo estriado, que está involucrado en los trastornos del espectro compulsivo, también está involucrado, no en las relaciones sociales humanas, sino en nuestra capacidad para relacionarnos. Así que profundicé en un campo llamado neurociencia social. Es un campo interdisciplinario más nuevo donde encontré informes que unían el cuerpo estriado no solo con anomalías sociales en ratones, sino también en las personas. Resulta que la neuroquímica social en el cuerpo estriado está relacionada con cosas que probablemente ya han oído: como la oxitocina, que es la hormona que hace que los abrazos se sientan cálidos y cómodos. También implica enviar señales a los receptores opioides. En el cerebro, hay opioides que ocurren naturalmente que están profundamente vinculados a los procesos sociales. Los experimentos con naloxona, que bloquea los receptores opioides, nos muestran que tan esencial es la señalización de los receptores opioides para la interacción social. Cuando las personas reciben naloxona, ingrediente en Narcan, se revierte una sobredosis de opioides para salvar vidas. Pero cuando se le administra a personas sanas, interfiere con su habilidad para sentirse conectados con personas que ya conocían y que les importaban. La falta de la unión entre los receptores y los opioides hace que nos resulte difícil sentir los beneficios de la interacción social. Para ser concisa, me deshice de ciertos detalles científicos, pero, en resumen, aquí estamos. Los efectos de la desconexión social a través de los receptores opioides, los efectos de las drogas adictivas y los efectos de una neurotransmisión anormal en los movimientos involuntarios y conductas compulsivas convergen en el cuerpo estriado. Y el cuerpo estriado y la señalización de opioides en él están profundamente relacionados con la soledad. Cuando los receptores opioides no tienen suficiente señal, nos sentimos solos en una habitación llena de gente que queremos y que nos quiere. Neurocientíficos sociales, como el Dr. Cacioppo en la Universidad de Chicago, han descubierto que la soledad es muy peligrosa. Predispone a las personas a espectros enteros de enfermedades físicas y mentales. Piénsenlo así: cuando están muy hambrientos, cualquier comida sabe deliciosa, ¿no? La soledad crea hambre en el cerebro, lo que neuroquímicamente, hipersensibiliza nuestro sistema de recompensa. El aislamiento social actúa a través de receptores para que los opioides naturales y otros neurotransmisores sociales dejen al cuerpo estriado en un estado donde la respuesta a cosas que indiquen recompensas y placer sea completamente extrema. En este estado de hipersensibilidad, nuestros cerebros indican una gran insatisfacción. Nos ponemos inquietos e irritables y nos volvemos impulsivos. Y ahí es cuando quiero que dejen los chocolates de Halloween del otro lado de la habitación porque me los comeré todos. Lo haré. Y esto trae otra cosa que hace que la desconexión social sea tan peligrosa. Si no tenemos la habilidad de conectar socialmente, estamos tan desesperados por rebalancear nuestra neuroquímica social que buscamos cualquier forma de alivio. Y si eso es analgésicos o heroína, será como un misil guiado a nuestro sistema de recompensa social. ¿Nos llama la atención que hoy en día la gente se vuelva adicta tan fácilmente? El aislamiento social, discúlpenme, contribuye a las recaídas. Los estudios han demostrado que las personas que evitan las recaídas son aquellas con relaciones sociales amplias y recíprocas donde pueden ayudarse el uno al otro, donde cumplen una función. Ayudar a alguien permite conectar a las personas. Así que, si no tenemos la habilidad de conectarnos auténticamente, nuestra sociedad cada vez carece más de esta habilidad y de experimentar cosas que son trascendentales y que nos superan. Antes la obteníamos de un sentimiento de pertenencia en nuestras familias y comunidades. Pero las comunidades están cambiando en todas partes. Y la desintegración social y económica hacen que esto sea cada vez más difícil. No soy la única que señala que las áreas del país con mayor dificultad económica, donde las personas sienten más desolación sobre el significado de su vida, también son los lugares donde más comunidades han sido afectadas por los opioides. El aislamiento social actúa a través del sistema de recompensa del cerebro y hace que la situación sea realmente dolorosa. Quizás es este dolor, esta soledad, este desaliento lo que nos está llevando a conectar con lo que sea que podamos. Como la comida. Como los aparatos electrónicos. Y para muchos, con drogas como la heroína y el fentanilo. Conozco a alguien que tuvo una sobredosis, y que fue revivida con Narcan, y estaba muy furiosa porque no la dejaban simplemente morir. Piensen como se siente eso, ese estado de desesperanza. Pero el cuerpo estriado también es una fuente de esperanza. Porque nos da una pista de cómo traer de vuelta a las personas. Recuerden que el cuerpo estriado es nuestro piloto automático, dirige las conductas según hábitos, y es posible recablear, reprogramar ese piloto automático, pero requiere neuroplasticidad. La neuroplasticidad es la habilidad de los cerebros de reprogramarse y recablearse para que podamos aprender cosas nuevas. Quizás escucharon el clásico adagio de la plasticidad: neuronas que se activan simultáneamente, refuerzan la sinapsis. ¿Cierto? Necesitamos practicar conductas de conexión social en vez de conductas compulsivas cuando estamos solos, cuando se nos estimula a recordar nuestra droga. Necesitamos disparos neuronales de experiencias repetidas para que el cuerpo estriado consiga la neuroplasticidad necesaria que le permite apagar el piloto automático del "ve a buscar heroína". La convergencia de la neurociencia social, la adicción y los trastornos del espectro compulsivo en el cuerpo estriado sugieren que no se trata solo de enseñarle al cuerpo estriado mejores respuestas a los impulsos compulsivos. Debemos reemplazar conductas compulsivas inducidas por drogas con impulsos sociales porque debemos rebalancear nuestro sistema de recompensa social neuroquímicamente. Si esto no sucede, quedaremos en un estado de ansiedad. Sin importar qué hagamos repetidamente además de nuestra droga. Creo que la solución a la crisis de opioides es investigar cómo las intervenciones sociales y psicoespirituales puede actuar como neurotecnologías en circuitos que procesan recompensas sociales e inducidas por drogas. Una posibilidad es crear y estudiar herramientas escalables para que las personas se conecten mediante un interés mutuo en la recuperación psicoespiritual. Estas prácticas psicoespirituales comprenden personas juntándose por ser grandes fanáticos de una banda, grupos de parkour que comparten experiencias de vulnerabilidad y crecimiento personal y cosas más convencionales como encuentros de yoga recuperativo y reuniones que se centran en concepciones más tradicionales de experiencias espirituales. No importa cuál sea, pero debe activar todos los sistemas de neurotransmisores en el cuerpo estriado que están involucrados en procesar la conexión social. Las redes sociales no ayudan lo suficiente. Las redes sociales no nos estimulan a compartir, sino a comparar. Es la diferencia entre tener una conversación superficial y una conversación auténtica y profunda con contacto visual. Y el estigma también nos separa. Hay mucha evidencia que nos mantiene enfermos. Y el estigma muchas veces facilita que los adictos conecten con otros adictos. Pero los grupos de recuperación que buscan restablecer la conexión social podrían incluir a las personas que buscan recuperarse de un amplio grupo de enfermedades mentales. El punto es que, cuando nos conectamos a través de algo que está roto, nos conectamos como seres humanos. Nos sanamos de la autodestrucción compulsiva que fue la respuesta al dolor de la desconexión. Al pensar en enfermedades neuropsiquiátricas como un espectro de fenómenos que es parte de lo que nos hace humanos, eliminamos la alteridad de las personas que luchan con la autodestrucción. Eliminamos el estigma entre doctores, pacientes y cuidadores. Devolvemos la pregunta de qué significa ser normal versus estar enfermo al espectro de la condición humana. Y es en ese espectro donde todos podemos conectarnos y buscar sanar juntos todas nuestras luchas humanas. Gracias por dejarme compartir. (Aplausos)